<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The declaration of Colonell Goring to the House of Commons, together with Mr Henry Piercies letter, to the Earle of Northumberland. And presented to the House of Commons the 16 of June, 1641</title>
            <author>Goring, George Goring, Baron, 1608-1657.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1641</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A85456</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing G1303B</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R177492</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99896633</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99896633</idno>
            <idno type="VID">170762</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A85456)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 170762)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 2429:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The declaration of Colonell Goring to the House of Commons, together with Mr Henry Piercies letter, to the Earle of Northumberland. And presented to the House of Commons the 16 of June, 1641</title>
                  <author>Goring, George Goring, Baron, 1608-1657.</author>
                  <author>Percy, Henry, Baron Percy of Alnwick, d. 1659.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 5, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed 1641.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Place of publication from Wing (CD-ROM edition).</note>
                  <note>Identified as Wing G1303B, reel 2429, of the UMI microfilm set "Early English books 1641-1700".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Folger Shakespeare Library.</note>
                  <note>Identified by ESTC as Wing (CD-ROM, 1996) G1303BA.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  Civil War, 1642-1649 --  Sources --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-11</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>John Latta</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:170762:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE
DECLARATION
OF
Colonell Goring.
To the houſe of COMMONS,
Together with
M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> Henry Piercies
LETTER, to the EARLE of
<hi>Northumberland.
And Preſented to the Houſe of</hi>
COMMONS the 16 of June,
1641.</p>
            <p>Printed 1641.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="declaration">
            <pb facs="tcp:170762:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:170762:2"/>
            <head>The Declaration of Colonel GORING, to
the houſe of COMMONS.
Together with Maſter HENRY PIERCIES
Letter to the Earle of Northumberland,
preſented to the Parlament the
16 of Iune 1641.</head>
            <p>WHat with my owne innocency, and the violence I hear
is againſt me, I find my ſelfe much diſtracted, I will not
aske your Counſel, becauſe it may bring prejudice upon
you, but I will with all faithfulneſſe and truth tell you what my
part hath bin, that at leaſt it may be cleared by you, whatſoever be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes
of me.</p>
            <p>When there was 50000 <hi>li.</hi> deſigned by the Parliament for the
Engliſh Army, there was as I take it, a ſudden demand by the <hi>Scots</hi>
at the ſame time of 25000 <hi>li.</hi> of which there was 15000 <hi>li.</hi> ready,
this they preſſed with much neceſſity, as the <hi>Parliament,</hi> after an
order made, did thinke it fit for them to deduct 10000 pound out
of the 50000 <hi>li.</hi> formerly granted, upon which, the ſouldiers in
our hoſt were much ſcandalized, amongſt which I was one, and ſit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting
by <hi>Wilmot,</hi> and <hi>Aſhburnham, Wilmot</hi> ſtood up and told them, if
that of the Scots would procure money, hee doubted not but the
Officers of the Engliſh Army might eaſily doe the like, but the firſt
order was reverſed, notwithſtanding, and 10000 <hi>li.</hi> given to the
Scots, this was the cauſe of many diſcourſes, of diſlike amongſt us,
and came to this purpoſe, that they were dis-obliged by the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,
and not by the King, this being ſaid often to one another,
we did reſolve that <hi>Wilmot, Aſhburnham; Pollard, Oneale,</hi> and my ſelf,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:170762:3"/>
to make ſome expreſſions of ſerving the King, in all things he wold
command us, that were honourable for him and us, being likewiſe
agreeing unto the fundamentall Lawes of the Kingdome, that ſo far
we would live and dye with him, this agreed upon with us, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving
any communication with others, that I am coupled now with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all,
and further by their joynt conſent, I was to tel his Majeſty thus
much from them, but withall I was to order the matter ſo, as the
King might apprehend this, as a great ſervice done vnto him, at
this time, when his affaires were in ſo ill a condition, and they
were moſt confident, <hi>that they would engage the whole Army thus far,
but further they would undertake nothing, becauſe they would neither infringe
the liberties of the ſubiects, or deſtroy the Lawes,</hi> to which I and every
one conſented, and having their ſence, I drew the heads up in a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
to the which they all approved, when <hi>I</hi> read it, and then wee
did by an oath promiſe one an other to be conſtant and ſecret in all
this, and did all of us take that oath together, then I ſaid, Well
Sirs, I muſt now be informed what your particular deſires are, that
ſo I may be the better able to ſerve you, which they were pleaſed to
doe, and ſo I did very faithfully ſerve them therein, as far as I could:
this is the truth, and all the truth upon my ſoule. In particular diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſes,
after that, <hi>we did fall upon the petitioning to the King and Parli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ament
for monies, there being ſo great arreares due to us, and ſo much delayes
made in the procuring of them, but that was never done.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>1. Concerning the Biſhops functions and votes.</p>
            <p>2. The not diſbanding of the Iriſh Army, untill the Scots were disban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
too.</p>
            <p>3. The endeavouring to ſettle his Maieſties Revenue to that proportion it
was formerly.</p>
            <p>And it was reſolved by us all, if the King ſhould require our aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance
in thoſe things, that as far as we could we might contribute
thereunto, without breaking the Lawes of the Kingdome. And in
caſe the King ſhould be denyed thoſe things, being put to them, wee
would not fly from him, al theſe perſons did act and concur in this
as well as I, this being all imparted to the King by me from them,
I perceived he had bin treated with by others, concerning ſome
things of our Army, which not agreed with what was purpoſed
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:170762:3"/>
by me, but inclined a way more ſharpe, and high, not having limits either
of honour or Law, <hi>I</hi> told the King he might be pleaſed to conſider with
himſelfe what ſhould be done, which way it was fit for him to hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
unto, for us we were reſolved not to depart from our grounds, wee
ſhould not be diſpleaſed, whoſoever they were, but the particular of the
deſignes, or the perſons we deſired not to know, though it was no hard
matter to gueſſe at them. In the end I beleev the danger of the one, the juſtice
of the other made the King tell me he would leave all thoughts of other
propoſitions but ours, as things not practiceable, but deſired, notwith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding
that <hi>Goring</hi> and <hi>Iermin,</hi> who were acquainted with the other pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings
ſhould be admitted amongſt us, <hi>I</hi> told him I, though the other
Gentry would never conſent to it, but <hi>I</hi> would propoſe it, which I did,
and we were all much againſt it; but the King did preſſe it ſo much, as at
the laſt it was conſented unto, and <hi>Goring</hi> and <hi>Iermin</hi> came to my Chamber,
there I was appointed to tell them after they had ſworne to ſecrecy, what
we had propoſed, which <hi>I</hi> did, but before I goe into the debate of the
way, I muſt tell you <hi>Iermin</hi> and <hi>Goring</hi> were very earneſt <hi>Suckling</hi> ſhould be
admitted, which we did all decline, and was deſired by all our men to be
reſolute in it, which I was, and gave many Reaſons: whereupon Maſter
<hi>Goring</hi> made anſwer, he was enggaed with <hi>Suckling,</hi> his being imployed in the
Army, but for his meeting with us, they were contented to paſſe it by.
Then we tooke up againe the wayes which were propoſed, which tooke
great debate, and theirs differed from ours in violence and height, which
we all proteſted againſt, and parted, diſagreeing totally, yet remitted it
to be ſpoken of by me and <hi>Iermin</hi> to the King, which we both did, and the
King conſtant to his former Reſolutions told him, theſe wayes were all
vaine and fooliſh, and would thinke of them no more, I omit one thing of
Maſter <hi>Goring,</hi> he deſired to know how the chiefe Commanders were to be
diſpoſed off, for if he had not a condition worthy of him, he would not go
along with us, we made anſwer that no body thought of that, we intended
if we were ſent downe to goe all in the ſame capacity we were in, he did
not like that by no meanes, and that did worke ſo with Maſter <hi>Chidley,</hi> that
there was a Letter ſent by ſome of the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>manders to make him Lieutenant
Generall, and when he had ordered this matter at <hi>London,</hi> and Maſter <hi>Chid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ley</hi>
had his inſtructions, then did he goe to <hi>Portſmouth,</hi> pretending to be ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
when this was a working, we all deſired my Lord of <hi>Eſſex</hi> and <hi>Holland,</hi>
that if there were a Generall at <hi>Newcaſtle,</hi> they were pleaſed to give out a
report that <hi>I</hi> ſhould be Generall of the Horſe, but I proteſt neither to the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:170762:4"/>
King nor any elſe, did I ever ſo much as think of it, my Lord of <hi>Holland</hi> was
made Generall, and ſo all things were layd aſide, and this is the truth and
all the truth I knew of theſe proceedings, and this I will and doe proteſt
unto you upon my faith, and <hi>Willmat, Aſhburnham,</hi> and <hi>Oneale,</hi> have at ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall
times confeſſed and ſworne, I never ſaid any thing in the buſineſſe, they
did not every one agree unto and would juſtifie: this Relation I ſent you
rather to informe you of the truth of the matter, that you may the better
know to doe me good, but I ſhould thinke my ſelfe very unhappy to be
made a betrayer of any body: what concerned the Tower or any thing elſe.
<hi>I</hi> never medled withall, nor never ſpake with <hi>Goring,</hi> but that night before
them all, and I ſaid nothing but what was conſented unto by any party, <hi>I,</hi>
never ſpake one word with <hi>Suckling, Carnarvan, Davenant,</hi> or any other crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture,
me think, if my friends and kindred knew the truth and juſtice of
the matter, it were no hard matter to ſerve me in ſome meaſure.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="declaration">
            <head>Colonell Gorings Declaration on his Examinati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,
concerning the late Conſpiracie againſt the State.</head>
            <p>HAving beene told there was an intention to unite the forces of our
Army, and to put it into a poſture of being able, if not of purpoſe of
being willing to interpoſe in the proceedings of Parliaments,</p>
            <p>I hearkend to the propoſitions of ſolliciting a redreſſe, for the miſeries
of the Souldiers being the firſt ſtep to this, in reſpect of the preſent neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities
of it, not any future conſequence of trouble to thoſe, that were to
procure our reliefe.</p>
            <p>But leſt the manner of asking this or the effects of it, being obtained,
might be leſſe juſt, then the thing it ſelf which was deſired, &amp; I might be in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volved
their crime that had, further ends, perhaps then meerly the redreſſe
of our Armies grievances: I thought it not unſafe to take ſome witneſſe
of mine integrity along with me, and ſpoke to a noble Lord the very ſame
day when I aſſured him there were ſome Officers of the Army, that were
leaſt thought on, that had greateſt zeale to the proceedings of this Houſe,
&amp; I thought there would be an occaſion to let him know more of it: within
few dayes after, this Maſter <hi>Iermin</hi> and I being admitted into a Conſulta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion,
where we were tyed to ſecrecy by an Oath, in the company of thoſe
Gentlemen I have named in my Depoſitions, where their purpoſe was de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clared
to us in ſome Propoſitions, which were to this effect.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:170762:4"/>
            <p>1. First putting our Army into a posture to ſerve the King.</p>
            <p>2. Secondly ſending a Declaration to the Parliament, containing that no Act of
Parliament ſhould be made contrary to any former Act, which was expreſſed that Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacie
would be kept up as it is now.</p>
            <p>3. Thirdly, and that the Kings Revenue ſhould be eſtabliſhed.</p>
            <p>This I thought unlawfull for our undertakings, ſince I thought they in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended
to interpoſe the determinations of this Houſe, and it belongs
to an Armie, to maintaine, not to contrive Acts of State.</p>
            <p>I objected therefore againſt the propoſitions, and preſſed more the fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies
and difficulties, then the illegalities of them, not onely becauſe I
thought reaſon a greater Argument with them then Conſcience, but be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
I am ſo unhappy of the two, 2 be thought a worſe <hi>Common-wealth's</hi> man,
then a Souldier, and in that quality could procure moſt credit to my
words, and I endeavoured to ſhew them that as the Deſigne would be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pious,
if their moſt deſperate Counſell had beene followed, ſo it would
have beene the weakeſt that ever was undertaken, if it were admitted.</p>
            <p>And whereas I am ſaid to have a part in this violent Counſell; till the
day before this meeting, I never heard word of it, &amp; knew not when <hi>I</hi> came
to the Roome, whether theirs were not the ſame with the other, this they
may witneſſe for me, and that I declared, that <hi>I</hi> would have to doe with
neither, and that <hi>I</hi> expreſſed a contempt in our meeting in that manner,
but I relie upon the Teſtimony of ſome noble Lords of his Majeſties Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell,
and others, how I proteſted againſt all thoſe violent Counſells, even
in the birth of them, and with what pitty <hi>I</hi> looked towards the perſon of
his Majeſty, and the whole Kingdome in this buſineſſe.</p>
            <p>I appeale alſo to them, and to ſome members of this Houſe, what my
carriage was toward theſe Gentlemen, that were embarked in theſe un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertakings,
intending rather to prevent a miſchiefe, by abandoning their
Counſells, then to ruine them, by diſcloſing them: but miſtake me not, for
had <hi>I</hi> knowne of any former plot proceeded in, that would endanger or
diſturbe the quiet of his Majeſty, or the peace of this Kingdome, <hi>I</hi> ſhould
not have beene contented with declaring mine owne innocencie, nor have
ſtayd till the command of this Houſe, or an Oath extorted from me, a diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>covery:
but by a haſty open Declaration, have broken the bonds of amity,
and friendſhip, and all former tyes, to preſerve the duty of a Subject, and
as freely expoſed the knowledge of all to the view of the world, as <hi>I</hi> have
beene tender in publiſhing theſe purpoſes, even to my neareſt friends,
which had weight enough to cruſh nothing but the undertakers of it, and
certainely if they had ſtayd where <hi>I</hi> left them, there was no concluſion at
all. It appeares there were two ſeverall intentions digeſted by others, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
they were Communicated to me; And <hi>I</hi> knew not whether my hark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
to them were a fault, but <hi>I</hi> am ſure it was no misfortune.</p>
            <trailer>Finis.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:170762:5"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
